A Guide to the Carneal and Johnston, University of Richmond, Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1909-1976
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Carneal and Johnston, University of Richmond, Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1909-1976
Library of Virginia
40199
1210 sheets of mostly linen and vellum, some blueprints, some Diazoprints, some tracing paper (114 x 89 cm. and smaller)
Carneal and Johnston (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ballou, Justice, Upton, Architects, Glen Allen, Virginia, 07 August 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Leigh Carneal, Jr. and James Markam Ambler Johnston began their firm around 1908 after spending a year working independently out of the same office space. The firm went on to become one of the most prolific and long-established architectural practices in Virginia.
Carneal, born in Richmond on October 24, 1881, graduated in 1903 from the Virginia Military Institute. He began his architectural practice around 1906 following a three year stint as a clerk in his father's company, Sitterding-Carneal-Davis Company. Johnston, born in Rockbridge County on May 18, 1885, studied engineering at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and Cornell University before moving to Richmond in 1906. He worked at the Richmond Cedar Works for one year until he began his own architectural practice.
From 1908 until 1950, the firm of Carneal and Johnston (the firm was known as Carneal, Johnston, and Wright from 1928 through 1945, when Oscar Pendleton Wright was a partner) helped to mold the architectural environment of central Virginia, especially Richmond. Responsible for over 1300 buildings, Carneal and Johnston practiced in a wide-range of project types, from the mundane to the monumental. While they did execute some residential buildings, the firm generated a far greater number of public, commercial, and industrial structures. Some of their most notable structures include First Virginia Regiment Armory (1913), the Virginia Mutual Building (1919-1921), the Virginia State Office Building (1922-1923), Saint Joseph's Villa (thirteen buildings, 1930-1931), the Virginia War Memorial (1932), and various structures on the campuses of Richmond College (now the University of Richmond) and Virginia Military Institute.
The firm survived following the founders' retirements in the 1950s. Subsequent owners were Miles Cary Johnston, James Beck, and Raymond Browder who sold the firm to employees Carlos H. Costas, W. Fred Hughes III, and Kenneth E. Bunch in 1984. In 1999, the surviving firm of Carneal and Johnston merged with Ballou Justice & Upton, Architects, and ceased to exist as an architectural firm.
Scope and Content
The Carneal and Johnston University of Richmond architectural drawings and plans collections consists of 1210 sheets representing approximately forty-one distinct commissions as well as additional materials. The collection has been broken into two series. Series have been arranged for Commissions and Other Firms. The collection is housed in both rolled storage boxes and map cases. In some cases, due to the size of some materials, portions of a drawing set for a single commission may be located in both rolled storage and flat storage. The appropriate notations have been made to the finding aid in the form of a "see also" reference. The drawings have been organized by drawing title. Drawings without commission numbers have been noted as such and are identified only by their title. The date given on the container list is taken from the earliest date on the drawing and does not represent any revisions or addenda. This collection contains only architectural drawings and plans. No related correspondence or other documentary materials for the Carneal and Johnston firm are extant.
Series I- Commissions- This series is arranged by drawing title and represents work undertaken by the firm in its own right. The drawings sets typically consist of architectural, mechanical, electrical, and plumbing drawings. Some drawing sets include full-scale detail sheets on very long tracing paper. Commission # 1472 (Dormitory # 3) includes tracings entitled "V.[irginia] P.[rofessional] I.[nstitute] School of Business Administration." It is unclear the inclusion of this drawing represents incorrect filing or that Carneal and Johnston used the V.P.I. building in its design features for the University of Richmond project.
Series II- Other Firms- This series is arranged by drawing title and represents blueprint copies of designs executed by other firms for University of Richmond. The Carneal and Johnston firm probably used these original design drawings in their planning for later additions to the buildings. The firm of Cram, Goodhue, and Ferguson of Boston, Massachusetts and Richmond, Virginia, architect Charles M. Robinson are represented.
Arrangement
By drawing title.
Contents List
- Commissions
  This series is arranged by Carneal and Johnston commission number, if available, and represents work undertaken by the firm in its own right. The drawings sets typically consist of architectural, mechanical, electrical, and plumbing drawings. Some drawing sets include full-scale detail sheets on very long tracing paper. Commission # 1472 (Dormitory # 3) includes tracings entitled "V.[irginia] P.[rofessional] I.[nstitute] School of Business Administration." It is unclear if this drawing is included because it represents incorrect filing or because Carneal and Johnston used the V.P.I. building's design features in the University of Richmond project.
  - Dining Hall and Kitchen Additions for Westhampton College [North Court]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 18] 1947, 3 sheets (Box 8)
  - Student Activities Building [Political Science Building]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 16] 10/11/1951, 5 sheets (Box 5)
  - Dormitory for Women [Gray Court] 4/2/1973, 46 sheets (Box 6)
  - Dormitory for Women [Gray Court]- UNBUILT 10/13/1972, 36 sheets (Box 7)
  - T. C. Williams School of Law- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 5] 9/29/1952, 10 sheets (Box 4)
  - School of Business Administration- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 3 and Box 9] 1960, 7 sheets (Box 8)
  - School of Business Administration- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 3 and Box 8] 1960, 13 sheets (Box 9)
  - Dormitory No. 4 [Freeman Hall]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 21 and Box 10] 1964, 10 sheets (Box 11)
  - Dormitory No. 5 [Moore Hall]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 23] 1967, 2 sheets (Box 11)
  - Dormitory No. 1 [Wood Hall]- Full Scale Details 11/4/1955, 11 sheets (Box 12)
  - Topographic Map of Part of Westhampton Property 2/13/1909, 1 sheets (Box 13)
  - Topographic Survey University of Richmond 1/1/1965, 18 sheets (Box 13)
  - University of Richmond Topographic Map 1/1/1971, 6 sheets (Box 13)
  - Fine Arts Building [Booker Hall of Music]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 20] 1966, 5 sheets (Box 10)
  - Dormitory No. 2 [Robins Hall] 5/23/1958, 36 sheets (Box 1)
  - Dormitory No. 4 [Freeman Hall]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 21 and Box 11] 1964, 7 sheets (Box 10)
  - Addition to Keller Hall 5/11/1962, 29 sheets (Box 1)
  - T. C. Williams School of Law, Alterations and Additions to 2/1/1971, 32 sheets (Box 5)
  - T. C. Williams School of Law- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 5] 9/29/1952, 10 sheets (Box 3)
  - Dormitory for Westhampton College [South Court]- Full Scale Details [See also Series I, Folder 4] 6/21/1946, 13 sheets (Box 2)
  - Ryland Hall, Alterations and Additions to 7/21/1969, 27 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 1)
  - Additions and Alterations to Buildings at Lombardy and Broad Streets 9/4/1964, 14 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 2)
  - School of Business Administration 9/15/1960, 58 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 3)
  - Air Conditioning System for University of Richmond School of Business Administration 6/1/1976, 6 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 3)
  - Dormitory for Westhampton College [South Court] [See also Box 2] 6/21/1946, 40 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 4)
  - T.C. Williams School of Law [See also Boxes 3-4] 9/29/1952, 29 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 7, Folder 5)
  - University of Richmond Athletic Center [Robins Center] 3/1/1970, 167 sheets (OS-No. 3, Dwr., Folder 6)
  - [Miscellaneous Drawings for University of Richmond Athletic Center- Robins Center] 1972, 8 sheets (OS-No. 3, Dwr., Folder 6)
  - President's House 9/10/1971, 22 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Hall, Electrical Alterations to 6/12/1970, 5 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 8)
  - Jeter Hall, Electrical Alterations to 6/12/1970, 5 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 8)
  - North Court, Westhampton College 6/4/1962, 31 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 9)
  - Athletic Center, Central Utilities to Serve [See also Commission # 1627] 10/15/1971, 18 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 10)
  - University of Richmond, Junior College and University College, Adams and Franklin Streets 2/6/1967, 15 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 11)
  - Refectory, Addition to 5/10/1943, 14 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 12)
  - Transformer Vault for Westhampton College 9/4/1947, 2 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 12)
  - Chapel, Alterations to 3/4/1941, 4 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 13)
  - Dormitories [Jeter and Thomas Halls], Alterations to 7/20/1938, 7 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 13)
  - Dormitories [Jeter and Thomas Halls], Alterations to 5/25/1943, 3 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 14)
  - Temporary Office Unit 12/16/1946, 5 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 14)
  - Locker and Shower Building 3/5/1963, 3 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 14)
  - North Court Rewiring 3/18/1963, 4 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 15)
  - Student Activities Building, Development of Attic 8/15/1963, 2 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 15)
  - Y. M. C. A. for Infrimary, Alterations to 6/18/1943, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 15)
  - Phi Delta Theta [International House] 8/13/1941, 9 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 15)
  - Electrical Distribution System 2/22/1955, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 16)
  - Student Activities Building [Political Science Building] [See also Box 5] 12/1/1949, 32 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 16)
  - Electrical Distribution System, Extension to 5/7/1956, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 16)
  - Maryland Hall, Alterations to [See also Series II, Folder 2] 8/11/1965, 2 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 8, Folder 16)
  - Refectory Building [Sarah Burnet Hall], Alterations and Additions to 4/1/1964, 67 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 17)
  - Dining Hall and Kitchen Additions for Westhampton College [North Court] [See also Box 8] 6/19/1947, 16 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 18)
  - Social Activities Building for Westhampton College [Keller Hall] 10/11/1935, 27 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 19)
  - Fine Arts Building [Booker Hall of Music] [See also Box 10] 2/28/1966, 74 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 20)
  - Dormitory No. 4 [Freeman Hall] [See also Boxes 10 and 11] 8/15/1964, 30 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 21)
  - Dormitory No. 3 [Dennis Hall] 9/21/1962, 46 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 9, Folder 22)
  - Dormitory No. 5 [Moore Hall] [See also Box 11] 11/10/1967, 47 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 23)
  - Refectory Building, New Kitchen Floor 7/8/1937, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 24)
  - Library for University of Richmond 7/18/1955, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 24)
  - Dining Hall Heating University of Richmond Westhampton College 1962, 1 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 24)
  - Micellaneous- tracings, blueline prints, photostatic copies for undated or unidentified projects n.d., 15 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 25)
  - Physics Building [Puryear Hall]- Charles M. Robinson 7/1/1929, 11 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 1)
  - Biology Building [Maryland Hall]- Charles M. Robinson 2/1/1932, 13 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 2)
  - Extension to Westhampton College- Cram and Ferguson 3/29/1920, 12 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 3)
  - Men's Dormitory No. 2 [Thomas Hall]- Cram, Goodhue, and Ferguson 1913, 14 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 4)
  - Power House, Richmond College- Cram, Goodhue, and Ferguson n.d., 12 sheets (Map Case 2, Dwr. 10, Folder 5)